Guide to the Frederick H. Burkhardt papers, 2002-2006.
Burkhardt, Frederick H. papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Frederick H. Burkhardt papers, 1983-2009.
4727
Frederick H., Burkhardt 1912-2007.
2.5 cubic feet.
Correspondence, Newspapers, Printed Materials, Publications
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
The collection includes correspondence, published articles, reprints, and clippings relating to Burkhardt's work on the life and work of Charles Darwin including the subjects: evolution, creationism, intelligent design, and the history of medicine.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Frederick H. Burkhardt received a scholarship to study at Columbia University and earned a bachelor's degree in philosophy in 1933. With a fellowship at Oxford University, he earned another bachelor's degree in 1935. Returning to Columbia, he completed a Ph.D. in philosophy 1940. His first teaching position was in philosophy at the University of Wisconsin-Madison. During World War II, he was recruited to work for the Office of Strategic Services. Burkhardt served as president of Bennington College in Vermont from 1947 to 1957. He then served as president of the American Council of Learned Societies (A.C.L.S.), from 1859 to 1874; during this time the organization expanded from 30 to 69 societies, and achieved financial stability. Burkhardt was also influential in the establishment of the National Endowment for the Humanities. He sat on the Board of the Alfred Harcourt Foundation from 1962 to 2004. From 1966 to 1973 he was a member of the New York Board of Higher Education, serving as chairman from 1969 to 1971. In 1986, Burkhardt edited a 19 volume edition of the complete writings of Henry James. Upon retirement from the A.C.L.S., he founded the Darwin Correspondence Project with Professor Sydney Smith. The Project, based in Cambridge, England, gathered letters to and from Charles Darwin for publication, and began with the publication of The Calendar of the Correspondence of Charles Darwin. Burkhardt directed the project for many years, and remained active in its editing until his death, contributing to the first 17 of the projected 32 volumes of The Correspondence of Charles Darwin (Cambridge University Press).
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The collection includes correspondence, published articles, reprints, and clippings relating to Burkhardt's work on the life and work of Charles Darwin including the subjects: evolution, creationism, intelligent design, and the history of medicine.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Burkhardt, Frederick H.,1912-2007.; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882.
Subjects:
Evolution (Biology)--Philosophy.; Creationism.; Intelligent design (Teleology); History of medicine.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Biographical material 2009 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Awards: Columbia University Award for Excellence 1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Awards: Morton N. Cohen Award on behalf to The Modern Language Association of America (1st award) 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Awards: Society for the History of Natural History 1997 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Awards: Robert McNeil reports that the Barra Foundation is establishing a research fund hin F.H.B.'s honor at American Philosophical Society (APS) 2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Awards: Thomas Jefferson Medal 2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Awards: Honorary Fellowship at Clare Hall, Cambridge, UK 2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Awards: Burkhardt fellows at APS 2004 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Awards: History of Science Society 2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Donation: Moselsio print to Bennington Museum 2008 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Papers from FHB study: Documentary Editing 1986-2007 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Papers from FHB study: A Brief Eye View of Evolution 2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Papers from FHB study: History of Medicine/History of Medicine 2004-2008 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Papers from FHB study: Debate about Creationism 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Miscellaneous correspondence with and from friends, staff, and family 2007 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Web sites 2000-2005 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Early clippings of background material: Three Different Versions of Darwin 1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Early clippings of background material: Early Clippings about Darwin 1983-2004 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Early clippings of background material: Life at Down 2002 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Early clippings of background material: Darwin and Annie 2001 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Darwin's Illness correspondence 2001-2005 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Darwin's Illness correspondence n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Darwin's Illness: articles on 1998-2005 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
- Articles - General 2004-2006 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
- Articles: Evolution/Darwin/Science 1996-2006 (Box 1, Folder 12-14)
- Articles: Intelligant Design 2004-2006 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
- Bruce Weber correspondence 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Constance Carter: John Philipps on Weald 2002-2006 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Elizabeth Dunn and Role Play Video Game 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
- Family Misc. 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Faulkner misc. 2006 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Gillian Feeley-Harnik 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Ines Katenhusen/Alexander Dorner 2002-2006 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Richard Milner 2002-2005 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Jim Moore Misc. 2004-2006 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Peter Stanlis Misc. 2001-2005 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Obituaries: Herman Goldstine, Kate Smith, Robert K. Merton, David Gil, Stephen Jay Gould, John H. D'Arms, Roy Porter 2001-2004 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Planning Efforts (Darwin Project Manual [draft?]) 1997-2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Articles by FHB: Darwin correspondence 2001-2003 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Selected Letters (General): general history: 1866 and 1867 selected letters, first galley 2004 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Selected Letters (General): general history: selected letters 1864s, 1865s [2004?] (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Selected Letters (General): general history: selected letters 1860-1865 2003 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Selected Letters (General): general history: selected letters 1864 [2003?] (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Selected Letters Translation 2004-2006 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Selected Letters: Foreward by Stephen J. Gould 2008 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Selected Letters: Announcement 2008 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Selected Letters: Search: list of correspondents whose CD letters have not been located n.d. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Sample of the way Selected Letters were chosen: FHB and Samantha Evans n.d. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- AB on FB's life? and history of DCP? n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10)